

SARTHAK MOHANTY

Monash University & CSIRO, Melbourne

Email : sarthak.mohanty@monash.edu, sarthak2235@gmail.com,

moh063@csiro.au.

Telephone:+61480226267

Languages: English, Hindi, Odia, Bengali, Sanskrit

Nationality: Indian







Summary:

Experienced academic specialising in atmospheric dynamics, with two published papers and three ongoing research projects. Currently a climate data scientist at the Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation (CSIRO), Australian Government. Recently submitted a thesis in atmospheric science at Monash University and holds a BS-MS dual degree in geoscience from the Indian Institute of Science Education and Research (IISER), Kolkata.

Research Interest:

• Monsoon Dynamics. •. Air-Sea Interaction. • Atmospheric dynamics. • Statistical Climatology. • Climate Modeling.

Skills & Abilities:

- **Programming Language :** Python, MATLAB, NCL, FERRET, Basics of Fortran
- Application Software: CDO, NCO, Basics of ArcGIS, Basics of ERDAS IMAGINE, Origin, GnuPlot, Grapher, Corel, SigmaPlot, GIMP, DataGraph, Basics of QGIS
- Technical skills: High-Performance Computing, Machine Learning, Parallel Computing

Publications:

- Mohanty, S., Jakob, C., & Singh, M. S. (2024). Australian summer monsoon bursts: A moist static energy budget perspective. *Journal of Geophysical Research: Atmospheres*, 129(1), e2023JD039048.
- Basu, S., Mohanty, S., & Sanyal, P. (2020). Possible role of warming on Indian summer monsoon precipitation over the north-central Indian subcontinent. *Hydrological Sciences Journal*, 65(4), 660-670.
- Mohanty, S., Singh, M. S. & Jakob, C. (2024). Australian Summer Monsoon: Reanalyses vs. Climate Models in Moist Static Energy Budget Evolution. *Journal of Geophysical Research: Atmospheres (revision submitted)*
- Mohanty, S., Jakob, C., & Singh, M. S. (2024). The Moist Static Energy budget of Australian Summer Monsoon Bursts in Climate Models: Insights from Present and Warming Climate Scenarios. (In preparation to submit in JGR Atmosphere)
- Mohanty, S. & Ramesh, N. (2024). Evaluating Fiji's Historical and Future Climate Using CMIP6 Models: Insights from Moisture and Moist Static Energy Budget. (*In preparation to submit in Journal of Climate*)

Research Experience:

PhD Thesis (January 2020 - October 2023): Australian Summer Monsoon: A Moist Static Energy Budget Perspective. (Thesis submitted). Guide: Prof. Christian Jakob, Dr. Martin Singh (Monash University, Melbourne)

- MS Thesis (July 2018-May 2019): Indian Monsoon Precipitation Variation; Role of Northern Indian Ocean Warming and increase in inter-ocean thermal gradient. Guide: Prof. Prasanta Sanyal, Dr. C. Gnanaseelan (IISER Kolkata, India)
- Project Assistant (July 2019 December 2019): Indian Monsoon Precipitation variation; Role of surface and upper tropospheric temperature. Guide: Prof. S.K.Mishra, Prof. S. Sahany (Indian Institute of Technology, Delhi, India)
- Summer Project (June 2017 August 2017): Long term analysis of Mixed Layer Heat Content in Northern Indian Ocean and its effect on Indian summer and Winter monsoon. Guide: Ms. Divya David (National Centre for Antarctic and ocean Research (NCAOR), Ministry of Earth Science, Govt. Of India)
- Summer Project (June 2016 July 2016): An extensive analysis of heat content and salinity on the upper Arabian Sea and its effect on Indian Summer Monsoon Rainfall. Guide: Dr. C. Gnanaseelan (ESSO-Indian Institute of Tropical Meteorology (IITM), Ministry of Earth Science, Govt. Of India)

Employment:

- * Climate Data Scientist (November 2023 present (full time)): Fidelity of CMIP6 models in assessing Fiji monsoon simulation through Analysis of Moisture, Moist static energy, and Circulation Budgets. Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation (CSIRO), Australian Government.
- Climate Data Scientist (April 2023 October 2023 (part time)): Climate Model Selection for the Climate Services for Agriculture's Application Ready Data for Fiji using statistical downscaling applying machine learning approach, collaborating with the Fiji government. CSIRO, Australian Government.

Education:

- Ph.D. Monash University, Australia (Thesis Submitted October 15, 2023)
- * BS-MS Dual Degree IISER, Kolkata, India 8.88/10 CGPA
- 12th Upendranath Junior College, Soro, Odisha, India 81%
- 10th Balukeswar High School, Soso-Kanpur, Odisha, India 90.2%

Workshop & Conference:

- Attended in General Assembly of European Geosciences Union (EGU) at Vienna, Austria, 2023
- Attended in Australian Meteorological and Oceanographic Society (AOGS) at Adelaide, Austria, 2022
- Attended in ARC Centre of Excellence for Climate Extremes workshop, 2023
- Attended in ARC Centre of Excellence for Climate Extremes Winter School, 2022
- Attended in ARC Centre of Excellence for Climate Extremes Winter School, 2020
- Attended in Australian Meteorological and Oceanographic Society (AOGS) at Adelaide, Austria, 2022
- Attended in General Assembly of European Geosciences Union (EGU) at Vienna, Austria, 2019

- Attended in international conference on Climate Change Impacts, Vulnerabilities, and Adaptation: Emphasis on India and Neighbourhood (CCIVA), IIT Kharagpur (February 26 - 2 March, 2019)
- Attended in international workshop on Land-Ocean-Atmosphere Interaction, Greenhouse Gases and Coastal processes organised by centre for climate and Environmental Studies, IISER Kolkata (July 25 August 4,2018)

Research Presentation:

- Oral Presentation in 2023 at EGU General Assembly: Australian summer monsoon bursts: A moist static energy budget perspective.
- Oral Presentation in 2022 at AMOS: Australian Summer Monsoon: Reanalyses vs. Climate Models in Moist Static Energy Budget Evolution.
- Poster Presentation in 2019 at EGU General Assembly: Increase in north-east monsoon precipitation by rapid Indian Ocean warming and a strengthening inter-ocean thermal gradient.
- Poster Presentation in 2018 at IISER-Kolkata: A stable isotopic approach to estimate the evapotranspiration contribution to hydrological cycle over coastal region of eastern India.

Awards & Scholarships:

- Graduate Research Completion Award (July 2023 October 2023)
- Co-funded Monash graduate scholarship (January 2020 July 2023)
- Deans International Postgraduate Research Scholarship (January 2020 October 2023)
- 2nd best MS thesis award in Department of Earth Sciences at IISER Kolkata (June 11, 2019)
- 2nd Prize in the oral presentation in technical session 1 (Ocean Dynamic and Processes) in CCIVA, 2019 (2 March, 2019)
- Selected for Innovation in Science Pursuit for Inspired Research (INSPIRE) fellowship by Department of Science Technology (DST), Government of India to pursue PhD. (January 2020 December 2024) (Not Availed)
- Selected for Innovation in Science Pursuit for Inspired Research (INSPIRE) Scholarship by Department of Science Technology (DST), Government of India. (July, 2014 May, 2019)
- Higher Education Scholarship (HE: MEDHABRUTI JUNIOR) by Department of Higher Education(DHE), Odisha , India (2011-2013)
- Pathani Samanta Mathematics Scholarship by Department of Higher Education(DHE), Odisha, India (2011-2013)

References:

Prof. Christian Jakob

Professor, School of Earth Atmosphere and Environment, Monash University

Email: christian.jakob@monash.edu

Dr. Martin S. Singh

Senior Lecturer, School of Earth Atmosphere and Environment, Monash University

Email: martin.singh@monash.edu

I hereby declare all the details and documents cited above are true as per best of my knowledge. Sarthak Mohanty